<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of the royall festiuities and juego de cañas (a turnament of darting with reedes after the manner of Spaine) made by the King of Spaine at Madrid, the 21 of August this present yeere, 1623. To honour the espousall treaties of the illustrious Prince of Wales, with the lady Infanta Maria of Austria. Before the departure of the Prince from his court: towards the sea-side, to take shipping for his returne into England. Composed by Doctor Iuan Antonio de la Peña, natife of Madrid, and faithfully translated out of the Spanish printed copie.</title>
            <title>Relation of the royall festivities.</title>
            <author>Peña, Juan Antonio de la, fl. 1623-1638.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09280</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19594</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106088</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841813</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841813</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6423</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09280)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6423)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 581:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of the royall festiuities and juego de cañas (a turnament of darting with reedes after the manner of Spaine) made by the King of Spaine at Madrid, the 21 of August this present yeere, 1623. To honour the espousall treaties of the illustrious Prince of Wales, with the lady Infanta Maria of Austria. Before the departure of the Prince from his court: towards the sea-side, to take shipping for his returne into England. Composed by Doctor Iuan Antonio de la Peña, natife of Madrid, and faithfully translated out of the Spanish printed copie.</title>
                  <title>Relation of the royall festivities.</title>
                  <author>Peña, Juan Antonio de la, fl. 1623-1638.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by G. Purslowe] for Henry Seyle, and are to bee sold at the Tygers Head in St. Pauls Churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The parenthetical phrase in the title is printed between square brackets.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6423:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6423:1"/>
            <p>A RELATION OF THE ROYALL Feſtiuities, and <hi>Juego de Can<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>as</hi> [A Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament of Darting with Reedes after the manner of
<hi>Spaine</hi>] made by the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> at <hi>Madrid, the</hi> 21
<hi>of Auguſt this preſent yeere,</hi> 1623.</p>
            <p>To Honour the Eſpouſall Treaties of the Illuſtrious Prince of WALES, with the Lady INFANTA MARIA of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before the departure of the Prince from his Court towards the Sea-ſide, to take ſhipping for his returne into ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Compoſed by Doctor</hi> Iuan Antonio de la Pen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a, natife of
<hi>Madrid,</hi> and faithfully tranſlated out of the Spaniſh printed Copie.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Henry Seyle,</hi> and are to bee ſold at the <hi>Tygers</hi> Head in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Pauls</hi> Churchyard. 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6423:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6423:2"/>
            <head>TO DON PHILIPPE PACHECO, <hi>Marqueſſe of</hi> VIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LENA, Duke of ESCALONA, and <hi>Count of</hi> SANTISTENAN, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Relation requires your Excellencie for a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coenas, aboue a thouſand o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Titles, becauſe you are a Perſon more intereſſed in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours of his Maieſty, ſhewed the day of Turneament to my Lady the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe of <hi>Miranda,</hi> and to my Lady the Marqueſſe her Neece, when he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured her houſe with his Royall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: And that your Excellencie hath now recouered your health, J thought <pb facs="tcp:6423:3"/>good to honour you with this preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in writing, of what you enioyed with your ſight and preſence, a while to entertaine you, being aſſured to bee pardoned for thoſe faults, which in this Treatiſe may occurre the ſame, beeing as ſecure to bee freed from all Court-Cenſure, by ſuch a Patrone, whoſe life and State Heauen euer make happy.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Doctor <hi>Iuan Antonio de la Pen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6423:3"/>
            <head>A RELATION OF THE ROYALL FESTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uities made by his Catholike Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, <hi>to honour the Eſpouſall Treaties of the Illuſtrious</hi> PRINCE <hi>of</hi> WALES, <hi>with the</hi> LADY INFANTA MARIA <hi>of Auſtria.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE KING, our Lord and Maſter, not content, nor ſatisfied with the Feſtiuities and Entertainements hitherto ſhewed to the Highneſſe of the Illuſtrious PRINCE of WALES, Prince CHARLES, Sonne to the KING of <hi>Great Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine;</hi> wherein, the Nobilitie, liberalitie, and glory of my Countrie of <hi>Madrid,</hi> and Caualeers of the Court, vpon ſundry occaſions had concurred, as by other Relations is made manifeſt; his Maieſty determined to conclude his Feſtiuities, publikely, in the great Market-place of the Towne. A worthy Amphithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ater, <pb n="2" facs="tcp:6423:4"/>whereon for the Monarch of the two worlds, to repreſent the memoriall of moſt renowned Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Solemnities, to burie them in obliuion, which in deſpite of enuie, new emulation and glory hath renewed. <hi>Munday,</hi> was the day appointed, beeing the one and twentieth of <hi>Auguſt:</hi> for which end, the Market-place ſet forth with that order, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and ornament, as is vſuall; allotting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient proſpect for theſe rarities, in the ſame erecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, made in the forme of Scaffoldes, ſo neceſſarie for the placing of many ſtrangers which were there, as alſo, being prouidently diſtinguiſht and ſeparated. The Councels of State, and Peeres of the Kingdome, tooke their places, after the accuſtomed manner. The
<hi>Panaderia</hi> was ſet forth with rich hangings, with two Canopies of crymſon cloth of ſiluer; Chaires, and Pillowes of the ſame, in the two principall Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folds allotted to the King and Queene, but that there was a little partition which ſeparated them; a reſpect as due to the Illuſtrious Prince of ENGLAND, the choſen Spouſe of her Highneſſe, as deſeru'd in his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; which lighting on ſo ſuperiour an obiect, might ſeeme to bee offended with any interpoſition to his eye. The renowned
<hi>Infanta Lady Maria</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded, and augmented this fauour; being clothed for this Feſtuitie, in the Princes colours, in white, as an vnſpotted Doue, after the Maieſtie of <hi>England.</hi> The manes of her Coach-horſes were twiſted vvith blue ribbands; A demiſe of the Noble Fleece of her future Spouſe: all theſe being premiſes, which ſeeme to giue aſſurance of what hath beene treated vpon. <pb n="3" facs="tcp:6423:4"/>There accompanied the Lady <hi>Infanta,</hi> the Lord <hi>Don Fernando,</hi> her brother, clothed in Romane Purple, that radient Sunne of the Church, euen as his Siſter is the reſplendent beames of true beauty. The Queene, our Lady, came in a Chaire of State, ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by mens hands, with her vſuall ſtate and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence: whom there followed, as the Stars the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter light, the Minions and Ladies, bringing with her the peoples benedictions. His Maieſtie, and their Highneſſes din'd this day in publicke, in the ſpacious Halles of the <hi>Panaderia:</hi> and about two in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, came in Coach into the Market-place, our Lord the King, the Prince of
<hi>Wales,</hi> and the Lord <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fante Don Carlos,</hi> braue with grauity, and graue in brauery. The King came apparrelled in blacke, with his Brother, and the Illuſtrious Prince in white: their habits diuided in faſhion, halfe after the Engliſh, and halfe after the Spaniſh manner; they entred the Scat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foldes, his Maieſtie giuing the right hand, as alwaies he did, to the Prince. Foure and twentie Charriots (being inuented moueable groues, and Fountaines brought to that place) began to diſperſe of their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors, after the vſuall manner: and about halfe an houre paſt two, the Marqueſſe of <hi>Rentin</hi> hauing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed it, and <hi>Don Fernando Verdugo,</hi> with requiſite gallantrie and authority, required in ſuch ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, by the Gate that iſſues out into the Imperiall Street, cauſing much delight, and awaking all mens deſires,
<hi>Leonardo,</hi> Sergeant Trumpet to his Maieſty, entered, richly clad, and on horſebacke, whom fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed ſixteene Kettle-Drums, threeſcore Trumpets
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6423:5"/>and Clarions, and foure and twenty Muſicians, all his Maieſties ſeruants, and with his Liuerie, which for this day, was of carnation Sattin, garded with ſiluer lace, and blacke welts, cut vpon ſiluer tynſell; large Caſſocks, Hats with blacke and carnation Plumes, Swords and Daggers hatcht with ſiluer, with ſiluer Hangers, twiſted with blacke ſilke; all mounted on goodly Horſes, with bridles of the ſame: and the Trumpets and Drummes had his Maieſties Armes on their Pennons, as glorious and entire as could be made, in the moſt famous triumph of the world. Then followed the Kings Querrie,<note place="margin">The Kings Querrie.</note> all the Kings Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, his Pages, and Officers leading the way, vnco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, before a rich Horſe, on which his Maieſtie was to runne, all exceeding braue and gallant: there came foure Groomes of the Stable, foure Farriers, with Powches of Crimoſine Veluet, and in them whatſoeuer was requiſite for the ſhooing of Horſes; twelue Lacqueys of note, &amp; ſixtie horſes of a brown bay, white and blacke trappings, with muzzlers of ſiluer, mixt white and blacke, couered with horſe-clothes of new and freſh Crimoſin Veluet, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing embroidred on them in cloth of Gold, the name of <hi>Philip</hi> the 4. &amp; his Royall Armes, with edgings of ſilke and gold, and frindge of the ſame: A Lacquey led euery Horſe with the right hand, in a Liuerie of carnation Sattin, hoſe and iacket laid with ſiluer and black ſilke lace, the forepart and bottome being cut vpon ſiluer tynſell, black hats, ſiluer hat-bands, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and black Plumes, Sleeues of Cloth of ſiluer, and ſiluer Furniture. There came forth forty Yong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters <pb n="5" facs="tcp:6423:5"/>of the Stables, after the Turkiſh manner, open Hoſes, Iackets and Bonnets of carnation Taffata; and after all the horſes, with wonderfull Maieſtie and Greatneſſe, they brought along leaning on their ſhoulders, a goodly Rider, with his mounting ſteps of fine Wood, in-laid with Liſts of Ebony, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with carnation Taffata, with frindges of gold and ſiluer. There followed this glorious ſight, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other no leſſe ſumptuous, of twelue Mules laden with bunches of Canes, couered ouer with cloathes of crimſon Veluet, and vpon it richly imbroidered, the Royall Armes, head-ſtalles of Silke, bits of Siluer, Pettrels, and Bridles of the ſame; on the ſides and fore-parts of the Mules, and on the tops of their heads and Saddles, were ſet carnation and blacke plumes, ſtrip't with ſiluer, which ſeem'd Mountaines of feathers, caſt ouer with gold: with euery one of them there went a Groome, or Youth, in a Liuery of the Lacqueys; all which, to the admiration of this order, and equipage, added a pleaſure and delight to the view. Preſently with the ſame order, and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page, entred the horſes of other troupes, the ſhew of the towne following, and the reſt of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, as their lot fell out, as betweene ſo great Princes to auoid diſcontentments of precedencie, it was agreed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The townes ſhow.</note>The honourable Towne of <hi>Madrid,</hi> ſent forth foure Trumpets on horſebacke, with capariſons of Orange-colour'd Taffata, laid with Siluer Lace, and the Trumpeters in Caſſocks of the ſame; blacke Hats lin'd with Orange-colour'd Taffata, Orange-co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour'd <pb n="6" facs="tcp:6423:6"/>Plumes, and ſiluer furniture, and foure and twenty Horſes with rich trappings, on whom were mounted foure and twenty Lacqueys in a Liuery of Orange-colour'd Taffata, Hoſe, and Mandillions and Girdles, and furniture of Siluer; orange-colour'd Hoſe, and Points, Hats, furniture and Plumes like to the Trumpets; white Targets, and orange-colour'd Bandels; and after them came the Maior of the Towne, diſcharging the place of chiefe Rider.</p>
            <p>There followed the towne troope, foure Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets of the Lord
<hi>Don Duarte,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Don Duarte</note> in a Liuery of tawnie Taffata, with gabbardines layd with ſiluer Lace, and Hats of the ſame, with tucks of ſiluer, tawny Plumes, and branches of ſiluer; at the bottome of them, ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer furniture, and tawnie hangers: They wore in their Trumpets pennons, the Armes of <hi>Portugall,</hi> and <hi>Caſtile;</hi> and the Trumpetters wore vpon their ſhoulder plightes, and on their breſts the ſame Armes; their Horſes with capariſons of tawnie Sat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, and furniture garded with Siluer Lace. Hee brought forth ſixe and thirty Horſe in rich trappings, and muzzelers, with white Targets, and tawnie Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, who were led by the right hand with as many Lacqueyes: and beſides theſe, there went along twelue other Lacqueyes of note, cloathed in the ſame colours, with tawnie Hoſe and Iackets, laid with ſiluer Lace, ſleeues of tawnie Sattin, buttons of Siluer, tawnie Baſes, white Liſts, and Roſes, ſiluer furniture, tawnie Hangers, black Hats, with wreathes and Hat-bands of ſiluer twiſt, and tawny Plumes: there went diſtributed among the horſes, after the <pb n="7" facs="tcp:6423:6"/>Turkiſh manner, twenty yong men, with tawnie Ribbons and Hoſe, bonnets of the ſame, and cloathes of Shag, wherewith to wipe and ſmooth the horſes, with their ſpeciall Rider, in great gallantry, and bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie, manifeſting his Royall bloud, and <hi>Portugall</hi> glory.</p>
            <p>That the precedent ſhew might no wayes bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated, it was rcquiſite the Duke of <hi>Infantado</hi> ſhould follow the luſtre and honour of the <hi>Mendozas.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Infantado.</note> He brought with him foure Trumpetters in foure white Freezado Mantles, with gabberdines of blacke Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maske, edged with ſiluer Lace, and the armes of the Mendozaes on their ſhoulders, breſts, and pennons of their Trumpets, blacke Hats, wreathes, &amp; bands of ſiluer, white and blacke Plumes, ſiluer furnirure, and hangers ſiluer and blacke, and the edgings of the skirts of blacke Damaske, imbroidered with ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. He brought with him forty horſes, flea-bitten, with blacke and white trappings, white Turkiſh barbes, white tayles and maynes, white Targets, and blacke Bandels, with the illuſtrious and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous blazon of the <hi>Aue Maria;</hi> the which, by reaſon of the oppoſition of colours, yeelded to the ſight a pleaſant obied. A Lacquey led euery horſe with his right hand, and there were eight and forty more, of note and reſpect, all in Hoſe and Iackets of blacke Sattin, garded with broad ſiluer Lace, ſiluer furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, hats with bands and wreathes of ſiluer, vvhite and blacke Plumes, white Baſes, and loopes of ſiluer Plate, with thirty ſixe Groomes clad in crimſon Taf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fata, with downe-cut open Hoſe, Iacquets and Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets <pb n="8" facs="tcp:6423:7"/>after the Turkiſh manner, and rubbing cloathes of Freezado on their ſhoulders: and after the laſt horſe, vpon another very faire and beautifull ſate the Rider.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Don Pedro de Toledo,</note>This Pompe of the Duke, was followed by <hi>Don Pedro de Toledo,</hi> the honour of
<hi>Caſtilian</hi> Knights: the Admiration, and wonder of ſtrange Nations. Foure Trumpets led in his troupe of horſe themſelues, vpon Sorrell horſes, in gabberdines of yellow-coloured Sattin, laid with gold Lace, Hats of Taffata, with wreathes and bands of Gold, white Plumes, guilt furniture and Spurres, with the Armes of the Houſe of <hi>Toledo</hi> on their breſts, and the falling of their ſhoulders; their horſes, with capariſons of the ſame the Trumpets had. Hee brought in with him thirtie Sorrell Horſes, all with capariſons of Cloth of Gold, and Muzlers of the ſame, white Targets and Bandell of Gold. As many Lacqueys led them along in their right hands, with eighteene others of reſpect and note, in a Liuery of hoſe loopt all ouer, cut and edged vvith broad gold Lace, laid vpon an inward lining of ſiluer Tynſell; Iacquets laid with Gold Lace, and cut vpon Tynſell, guilt Furniture, white Baſes, and ſleeues of Tynſell; Hats imbroidered round about with little Wind-mils of Gold, vvith white Plumes, and Tucks of ſiluer tynſell; and with them their Rider.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall.</note>Preſently then entred the Admirall of <hi>Caſtiles</hi> Troupe, with the ſame Maieſtie and Greatneſſe, as vpon all occaſions his Excellence is accuſtomed: there vvent before his horſe foure Trumpeters, in <pb n="9" facs="tcp:6423:7"/>long Coates of blacke Sattin, garded with Gold Lace, with his Armes on their breſts, falling of the ſhoulders, and pendants, the Horſe with cloathes of the ſame, blacke Hats, yellow and white Plumes, Hat-bands and wreathes of Gold, golden furniture, and their Farrier on foot, with a Sattin Powch, and that neceſſarie in it for the ſhooing of Horſes, which were thirtie in number, all of a Cheſſe-Nut coate or colour, with trappings of white and Gold; and eight of them which vvere to runne, had their tayles and Maynes plighted with ſhort gold twiſt, and ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Inuention, and that mou'd vvonder all ouer the place, blacke Targets, and Bandell of Gold, Lances with two heads, and with euery horſe a Lacquey; they being in all with thoſe of note and reſpect, ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie two, cladde in blacke, Hoſe and Iacquets laid With gold Lace, yellow Baſes, and blacke Liſts, with frindges of Gold, white ſhooes, and gilded furniture; blacke Hats, with wreathes, and bands of Gold, orange-colour, and white Plumes, and twelue ſtable groomes clad in Hoſe, and Iacquets of blacke Taffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, thwarted ouer with Laces of Gold, bonnets of the ſame, and wiping cloathes of coorſe cloth, and it gaue no ſmall contentment, to ſee in the Market-place a troope of them, ſlicking and ſmoothing the Admirals Horſe.</p>
            <p>The Troope hemn'd round about the Rider, and foure Trumpets of the
<hi>Count de Monterey</hi> followed,<note place="margin">Monterey.</note> with long Coates of white Sattin, Laces &amp; Flowers of Gold, Hats of the ſame, blacke Plumes, and gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den furniture, with his Armes vpon the Trumpets,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6423:8"/>and the Horſes that went with horſe-cloathes in the ſame Liuery. Hee brought with him fifty horſes of Cheſt-nut coat, in trappings of white &amp; gold, white Targets with white bandels, with Imagerie wrought in gold; the colours of the Illuſtrious PRINCE of WALES, who much fauoureth the <hi>Count.</hi> There came with them in all an hundred Lacqueys: their Liuerie was in white, leaues of gold and blacke Eſſes, golden furniture, blacke Hats, with wreathes, and bands of Gold, blacke and white Plumes, and twelue yong men of the Stable, after the Turkiſh faſhion, in the ſame Liuerie, blacke ſhooes and Bus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins gilded, and their Rider.</p>
            <p>There followed him the Marqueſſe of <hi>Caſtel-Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drigo</hi> his company a <hi>Portugeſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caſtel-Rodrigo.</note> who was conducted by an Vnder-Rider, and foure Trumpets on horſe-backe, with capariſons of greene Sattin, and ſiluer Lace: the Trumpeters themſelues, with Caſſocks of the ſame, and the Armes imbroidered on their pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons and Trumpets, white Bootes, Spurres and gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded furniture, blacke Hats wrought with ſiluer, and tawnie plumes. He ſhewed two and fortie different horſes, with rich trappings of purfle, gold and ſiluer, white Targets, and greene bandels, with fifty Lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queys in greene, hoſe and Caſſock laid with ſiluer Lace, ſleeues of tawnie taffata, with baſes and hoſe of tawnie, greene points and Roſes, with little im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broidered Wind-mils of ſiluer, gilded furniture, with tawnie hangers, blacke Hats, band and wreathe of ſiluer, and tawnie plumes, twelue Stable-groomes with Mandillions, hoſe and bonnets of green taffata, <pb n="11" facs="tcp:6423:8"/>with fixe capariſons of ſiluer-worke, and his Rid all in <hi>Portugall</hi> brauerie.</p>
            <p>To whom in emulation, ſucceeded the <hi>Caſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi> of the
<hi>Cordouas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seſſa.</note> in the company of the famous Duke of <hi>Seſa,</hi> who ſhewed glory and brauerie, proper to his Family. He brought foure Trumpets on horſeback, with Caſſocks of ſea-water greene, waued with gold Laces, hats of the ſame, with greene pennons, plated furniture, and his Armes vpon the Trumpets; the horſes with cloathes of taffata, of the ſame colour, and garded with ſiluer Lace. There followed them foure and thirty ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell horſes, with crymoſine trappings, and Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh barbes of the ſame colour, forty and two Lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queys, betweene the leaders and thoſe of note, with a Liuery of Sea-water greene, and ſiluer hoſe and caſſocks garded with lace, greene hoſe, and blue points, plated furniture, with blacke hats, wreathes and bands of ſiluer, and greene plumes, and their Rider with eight Lacqueys.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, incloſing theſe magnificent ſhewes, came in the Duke of <hi>Ceaes</hi> horſe,<note place="margin">Cen.</note> 
               <hi>Don Franciſco de Sandoual y Roias,</hi> with that hereditarie Greatneſſe bee deriues from his Grandfather: hee brought with him foure Trumpets in foure Freezado Coates, clad in gabberdines of blue Sattin, laid with ſiluer Lace, blacke hats, wreathes and bands of ſiluer, blue plumes, plated furniture, with black hangers; the hoſe with cloathes of the ſame Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie, and his Armes on the Trumpets; about foure and twenty horſe, with rich trappings of Pearles, Pouncings, Gold, Siluer, and Pomegra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates, <pb n="12" facs="tcp:6423:9"/>and amongſt them hee that is called the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uillano,</hi> vpon whom hee ranne his Canes: their targets were white with blue bandels, foure and twenty Lacqueys led them with the right hand, and 30 others of note, cloathed in blue ſackcloth, laid all ouer thicke with many ſiluer laces, blacke hats, wreathes and bands of ſiluer, blue plumes and baſes, points of ſiluer thread, white ſhooes, plated furniture, and their Rider all in blacke, with Lacqueys alſo in blacke, after a graue and modeſt faſhion. The Horſe were all in number, fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred twenty and three, with thoſe of the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, Kettle-drummes and Riders: and the Lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queys fiue hundred foureſcore and ſixe: twelue Muleters; Farriers, Horſe-keepers, and Stable-groomes, an hundred fortie and one: their entry continued aboue an houre. And hauing ſhewed, and made their obedience, they baited but a few Buls, to giue way to the running of the Canes.</p>
            <p>His Catholike Maieſtie, and the Lord <hi>infante Don Carlos,</hi> ſhewing their accuſtomed courteous complements to the Queene, the Prince, and the Lady <hi>Infanta,</hi> left their Scaffolds, and at a gate that goes into the ſtreet of <hi>Atocha,</hi> tooke Coach, Where an infinite concourſe of people atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their entry. The ſtreet reflected vpon by the Sunne, was ſanded, and watered, and the entries chain'd vp, a remedy againſt the cumberſome an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyance of Coaches, the diſturbance of Feſtiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which the prouidence of <hi>Don Iohn de Caſtilla</hi> preuented, as he vſeth to doe. Aduertiſement was giuen ſome few dayes before, to the Counteſſe <pb n="13" facs="tcp:6423:9"/>of <hi>Miranda,</hi> that his Maieſtie would honour her, by comming thither to maske himſelfe, and the Meſſengers were one day, the <hi>Marqueſſe de Flores Auila,</hi> and the other day <hi>del Infantado.</hi> Her Excellency entertained this fauour, proiuding her houſe, conformable to the ſhort warning ſhe had: ſhee whited it all ouer, euen to the ſtaires of Aſcent, ſetting forth the Court round with new Hangings, and hanging vp in all the entries or Portals of the Kings Quarter, Curtaines of white Damaske, with Gold Frindge, and Walking Rods guilded: There were beds laid for the King and the <hi>Infante,</hi> which were brought out of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, by the Duke of <hi>Infantados</hi> order, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted the Counteſſe in this one thing to follow his direction, though her Excellencie had proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thoſe that were moſt rich: but ſhe followed the Dukes counſell, as a friend, though it were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ancient cuſtome of her Houſe; who, in ſuch like entertainments, without hauing any thing from the Palace, had euer plentiful and honorable ſtore: the Roomes were waſhed with ſweet pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and water of Amber mingled, yeelding an excellent and comfortable odour to the ſenſes. Next to his Maieſties Quarter, ſhe prouided an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the <hi>Conde de Oliuares,</hi> with a rich bed of Needle-worke, and the Guſſets of the ſoft knap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings of Silke, and in the lower part of the houſe, a Quarter for
<hi>Don Iayme de Cardenas,</hi> who was this day one of the Gard, and appointed to cloath the King: for which purpoſe hee had prouided Gloues, Handkerchiefes, preſent collation, &amp; ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry <pb n="14" facs="tcp:6423:10"/>waters of delight. In the ſame manner vvas there prouided another Quarter for the Marqueſſe <hi>del Carpio,</hi> who was to attend the Lord <hi>Infante,</hi> and an other hang'd with crymſon Damaske fring'd with gold, for the Lords that would refreſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, with aboundance of conſerues, ſweet meats, and waters of all ſorts, and delightſome. She pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided ſhirts, for his Maieſtie and Highneſſe to change, at their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming or going, as they did. She gaue two Boxes for Reliques, of ineſtimable value, to his Maieſtie, with a famous relique of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Philippe</hi> the Apoſtle: to the Lord <hi>Infante,</hi> and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Lawrence,</hi> which
<hi>Pope Sixtus</hi> the 5. gaue to the Counteſſe, when ſhee was Vice-Queene of <hi>Naples:</hi> and the Galley wherein they came being ſunke, after a yeeres ſpace, the Trunk wherein they came, was ſeene in the water, which being known to belong to the <hi>Conde, Iohn Andrea Doria</hi> ſent it him; a miraculous accident, and which approues the certaintie of reliques, a pious and diſcreet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vpon ſuch an occaſion, &amp; to ſuch perſons: ſhe alſo had Gloues &amp; handkerchiefes for them, in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binets of Rock-chriſtal, wrought with gold, Paſts to be eaten, in glaſſes of the ſame: &amp; apples of ſweet waters, all chriſtall, and gold, and being moſt wiſe and diſcreet, to giue full contentment to his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, ſhe procured that in the Monaſtery of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Trinitie, the holy Sacrament ſhould be opened, with great ſolemnitie of lights and Ornaments, which his Maieſtie, and Highnes humbly ador'd, from the Counteſſes window, ſhewing the deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> euer had. At the <pb n="15" facs="tcp:6423:10"/>Counteſſes ſtaires, there receiued his Maieſtie the Ladies of <hi>Zunniga,</hi> and the firſt that kiſt his hand, was the Counteſſe of <hi>Monte-Rey,</hi> whom the King honoured, with laying his armes vpon her; the Lady of <hi>Nieua,</hi> and the Marquiſeſſe of <hi>Flores Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uila</hi> did the like, the Ladie of
<hi>Alcannizas,</hi> &amp; the two Counteſſes of <hi>Santiſteuan,</hi> and <hi>de Villa-A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonſo,</hi> to whom his Maieſtie vouchſafed the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie he vſually ſheweth to Ladies; and ſo paſſing through the midſt of them all, hee went directly to the Quarter of the Counteſſe
<hi>de Miranda,</hi> where her Excellencie attended; and being ſaluted by his Maieſtie, ſhe made ſute for his hand to kiſſe, with a briefe and modeſt diſcourſe, manifeſting the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour that herein ſhe receiued.</p>
            <p>After this, his Maieſtie went to maske him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, into his owne Quarter, where they had pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced a Royall Table, furniſh't with all manner of Conſerues, about fortie Plates and diſhes of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, with dry'd Suckets, and roſe-ſugar confecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of eight ſeuerall ſorts. The King taſted ſome of them, and commanded it ſhould ſtill ſtand rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy prepared till they returned from running. All this paſſed in the Counteſſes houſe, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo worthy to be imparted to thoſe curious to learne and know, I thought good in this diſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to make a digreſſon from ſetting downe the Feſtiuitie. And no great wonder that
<hi>Pihlip</hi> the fourth thus honoured the Counteſſe of <hi>Miranda,</hi> knowing that wiſe <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond, his Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, did as much, when ſhee was Vice-Queene of <hi>Barcelona,</hi> being accompanied with the Ladies <pb n="16" facs="tcp:6423:11"/>Infantaes, Lady <hi>Iſabella,</hi> and Lady
<hi>Catalina,</hi> when the Count had the Duke of <hi>Sauoya</hi> for his gueſt, and the greateſt part of his Court, for foure mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths in his own houſe and at his charges, imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in theſe fauours, <hi>Philip</hi> the third, the <hi>vertuous</hi> his Father, who in <hi>Vallodolid</hi> ſupped in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſes houſe, when the Duke was married, who is Duke of
<hi>Pennaranda,</hi> fauours due vnto his Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Houſe and Lady. The
<hi>Canes</hi> were now ſorted out, the Drummes, Trumpets, and his Maieſties Muſicians going before them, by the Streetes of the
<hi>Relators,</hi> and <hi>Atocha,</hi> euen to the Market-place; and before their entring it, <hi>Don Auguſtin Mexia,</hi> and <hi>Don Fernando Gyron,</hi> of the Councell of State and Warre to his Maieſtie, being valiant Souldiers, as all men know, made their Entries, as Patrons of the
<hi>Canes,</hi> to preſent them to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, and Highneſſes; preſently came in all the Muſicke,<note place="margin">The Kinge.</note> taking their places, when his Maieſtie, whom God preſerue for many yeeres, entred, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning againſt the <hi>Count de Oliuares</hi> (a deſerued ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of ſo faithfull a Prince) mounted on two brown bay horſes, with ſuch dexterity and force, and ſo iuſtly encountering in euery reſpect, that the earth enuying ſo equal a ſhock, remained with the immpreſſions and prints in it of this Carreere, making footſteps in the ſand, as a paterne and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample for ſuch as are accuſtomed to that exerciſe, and ſhall hereafter follow in the ſame place. At the Kings running, his Maieſtie and their Highneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, with the Councellors of the place, made a complementall Recognition. By and by, ran the <pb n="17" facs="tcp:6423:11"/>Lord <hi>Infante Don Carlos,</hi> renewing in the valour of his tender yeeres, the memoriall of his great Grandfather, and the Marqueſſe of <hi>Carpio</hi> ran a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, as euer he vſeth to do. There follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Don Lewys de Ato,</hi> an imitator of his Father, the Marqueſſe, &amp; with him ran <hi>Sant Estiuan, Don Iay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me de Cardenas</hi> encloſing the Troupe, brother to the Duke of
<hi>Maqueda,</hi> and the <hi>Count Portalegre.</hi> The veſtiments of his Maieſtie, and the Lord <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fante,</hi> were rich and coſtly, with Spaniſh Capes and Caſſocks of Carnation Sattin, embroidred with blacke ſilke and gold, white frizled ſleeues, and Plumes carnation &amp; black, and anſwerable to the Kings colours, was all the reſt of his Squadro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. By and by ran the Nobilitie of the Towne of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid,</hi> faithfull ſeruants to his Maieſtie; againſt whom, came <hi>Don Iuan de Caſtilla,</hi> their
<hi>Corregidor,</hi> and <hi>Don Lorenzo de Oliuares, Don Pedro de Torres,</hi> and <hi>Don Chriſtoual de Medina</hi> ſeconding them, all three Regidors,
<hi>Antonio de Herrera,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Towne.</note> and <hi>Don Franciſco de Garnica,</hi> maintaining the courſes, and <hi>Don Gaſpar de Guzman,</hi> and <hi>Don Sebaſtian de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treras,</hi> ending the Squadron, al in the habite of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iames.</hi> Their Liuerie was of orange-coloured Sat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, embroidred with leaues of Siluer plates of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, &amp; blacke ſilke, Bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nets with rich ſetting forth, and fairely ſpred with Orange-colour'd Plumes.</p>
            <p>Preſantly ran the Lord <hi>Duarte,</hi> with the Count of
<hi>Villamor,</hi> the encounter was braue, <hi>Don Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio de Meneſes,</hi> and the <hi>Count Pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>naflor</hi> maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it, there ſeconded them, <hi>Don Rodrigo Pimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel,</hi> and the <hi>Count Pu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nonroſtro,</hi> and the Marqueſſe <pb n="18" facs="tcp:6423:12"/>of <hi>Malagon,</hi> and the Duke of
<hi>Veraguas,</hi> ended this Squadron. Their Liuerie was rich and ſightly, Cape and Caſſocks of tawny Sattin, embroidred with ſiluer and blue, cut vpon ſiluer tynſell, with white Pennons, and tawny Plumes.</p>
            <p>By and by after, ran the Count of <hi>Tendilla,</hi> and the Marqueſſe of <hi>Mondejar</hi> his Father, the Duke of <hi>Infantado</hi> beginning the firſt courſe of the Squadron,<note place="margin">Infantado.</note> with their accuſtomed ſpirit and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour; one honouring another, as the fruit doth the tree, and the Father aſſiſting his Son, and giuing him his right hand. <hi>De Corunna,</hi> and <hi>Villar</hi> ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them, and with rare equality, <hi>de Annouer,</hi> and <hi>de la Peubla,</hi> the Marqueſſe of <hi>Belmar,</hi> and <hi>Don Diego Hurtado de Mendoza,</hi> Corregidor of <hi>Toledo,</hi> ending this Squadron. The Duke ran not with the <hi>Canes,</hi> both in reſpect of his venerable yeeres, as alſo for ſome other indiſpoſition of body. Their Liuerie was very fantaſticall, Capes and ribbons of black damask, embroidred with branch worke of ſiluer, cut vpon Tynſell, with white and black Plumes.<note place="margin">Don Pedro de Toledo.</note> The valour of the <hi>Toledos,</hi> conteſted in ſome ſort with the force of the <hi>Mendozaes,</hi> the Marqueſſe of <hi>Belada,</hi> and the Lord of
<hi>Higares</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning the courſe; the Marqueſſe herein ſhewing that agilitie and dexteritie, which with the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe of the people he ſhewes vpon all ſuch occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. In imitation of him, followed <hi>Don Luis Ponce,</hi> Nephew to the Duke of <hi>Arcos,</hi> and <hi>Don Franciſco de Eraſo;</hi> and ſo maintaining that which was well begunne, there followed <hi>Don Antonio de Auila</hi> and <hi>Toledo,</hi> Count of
<hi>Riſco,</hi> with the Lord <pb n="19" facs="tcp:6423:12"/>
               <hi>de la Horcajada: Riſco,</hi> as at all other times, performed it brauely: Laſt of all, to conclude the reſt, which was good, <hi>Don Pedro de Toledo,</hi> with <hi>Don Diego de Toledo</hi> &amp; <hi>Guzman,</hi> ended this Squadron. Their Liuerie was, Capes of Cloth of gold, vpon the Gold embroidred with ſiluer, Ribbons of cloth of Siluer, embroidered vvith gold; ſmall wreath'd hat-bands, and Bonnets with white Plumes, with blacke ſprigges, and open ſleeues.</p>
            <p>The laſt <hi>Toldeoes</hi> had ſcarce finiſhed their courſes, when, to continue admiration and delight, there en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred the
<hi>Admirall,</hi> and the Marqueſſe of <hi>Alcanizas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</note> a worthy couple, to renowne and celebrate the place, by the ſound their horſes made, with the gold twi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in their manes and tayles. <hi>De Tabarra,</hi> &amp; Count <hi>de Villalua</hi> ſeconded, with no leſſe brauerie. In emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of theſe, came in the Marqueſſe of <hi>Toral,</hi> chiefe of the <hi>Guzmans,</hi> and <hi>Don Antonio Moſcoſo, Don Diego de Silua,</hi> Marqueſſe <hi>de Orani,</hi> and the <hi>Count de Villaflor</hi> ending this Squadron. They had rich open ſleeues, blacke Feathers ſtrip't with gold, Ribbons and Capes of blacke Sattin; embroidered with Gold, and cut vpon ſiluer tynſell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Monte-Rey</hi> gaue occaſion of new commendation and praiſe, with the Marqueſſe of <hi>Camaraſa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Monte-Rey<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter of equall brauerie; who were ſeconded by <hi>Don Iuan Carlos de Guzman,</hi> and the Count of
<hi>Salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tierra, de Onate,</hi> and <hi>Don Pedro de Cardenas</hi> and
<hi>Angu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo,</hi> the Illuſtrous <hi>de Fromeſta,</hi> &amp; <hi>Don Iuan Eraſco,</hi> fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing the Squadron: all as gallant in their appearance, as ready and expert vpon their Gynnets. Their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie was white Sattin emboſſed with Gold, &amp; black <pb n="20" facs="tcp:6423:13"/>powncings, Mylan Bonnets, and blacke Plumes.</p>
            <p>There followed the Squadron of the Marques of
<hi>Caſtel-Rodrigo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caſtel-Rodrigo.</note> who ran with the Duke <hi>de Hijar,</hi> with ſuch equall valour and vvorthineſſe, that one could hardly iudge, whether it were one or two that ran, <hi>Don Lorenzo de Caſtro,</hi> and <hi>Don Dionis de Fare</hi> Portugals, followed, the Marques of <hi>Orellana,</hi> and <hi>Don Baltazar de Ribera.</hi> This Squadron ending in the Count <hi>de Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cla,</hi> and the Marques of <hi>Almazan.</hi> Their Liuery was of greene Sattin, imbroidered with ſiluer, the lining of Cloth of Siluer, and faire Bonnets, adorn'd vvith darke tawnie Plumes.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Seſſaes</hi> Squadron followed this, who ranne with <hi>Don Luys Vanegas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seſſa.</note> 
               <hi>A Poſentador Maior,</hi> both dextrous with valour, and valorous with dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, who were ſeconded, by the Lord <hi>de Sueros, Don Franciſco de Cordoua, Don Lewis de Rojas,</hi> and <hi>Don Diego de Guzman,</hi> the
<hi>Count de Cabra,</hi> and <hi>Don Iuan de Cordoua</hi> ending the Squadron, aduancing the equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of their firſt encounter. Their Liuery was very luſtrous. Sea-water greene Sattin, imbroidered vvith Siluer and blacke, blacke Plumes, ſtrip't with white, and faire and rich ſleeues.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, for the laſt ſeruice of ſuch Royall begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and Princely progreſſions,<note place="margin">Cea.</note> there ranne the Duke of <hi>Cea,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Eſquilache;</hi> the Duke bare himſelfe brauely, &amp; the Prince accompanied his own noble diſpoſition, with martiall dexteritie, <hi>de Penna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiel,</hi> and <hi>de Valle</hi> ſeconded them, a worthy emulation of ſuch Precedents: the Counts
<hi>de Mejorada,</hi> and <hi>de Cantillana</hi> imitated them: this Squadron ending, in <hi>Xabalquinto,</hi> and <hi>Don Chriſtoual de Gabiria.</hi> ſo ſpeciall <pb n="21" facs="tcp:6423:13"/>a runner, as vpon any occaſion hee hath euer mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted: Their Liuerie was of blue Sattin, Cloake and Caſſocke imbroidered with drafts, and raiſings of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, ſpots of blacke Silke and Siluer, with the lining of Cloth of Siluer, blue Turbants with ſeeing glaſſes (a witty conceit, becauſe in the glaſſe of euery end and concluſion, we may behold the worthineſſe of begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings) their Plumes were blue, large, and luſtrous, which on this day were ſo many in number, as it ſeemes incredible they could euer light vpon them, though not ſufficient to write ſuch magnificent Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uities as this, yet enow to blaze the Fame hereof to all the vvorld. After they had quarter'd out the place backe to backe, and ranne along the ſides thereof, they vvent to change Horſes, and take in hand their Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets, making their windings and diuiſions: The par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties being diuided into fiue Squadrons, for each one, his Maieſtie conducing ſome, and the Duke of <hi>Cea</hi> the reſt. The Canes were runne, as beeing guided by ſuch a Maſter: for certainly without allowing herein of any flatterie, or affection of a Subiect, this Maieſtie ranne the beſt of them all, and the Lord <hi>Infante Don Carlos,</hi> ſhewed himſelfe to be truely his Brother. The Duke of <hi>Cea,</hi> deliuered the Canes to the King, vvith that obſeruance which becomes a Subiect to his Prince. The whole place brake forth into generall acclamations:
<hi>May his Maieſtie liue long and many yeeres, and</hi> London
<hi>queſtionleſſe would now re-eccho to our ſounds, ſeeing his Maieſtie made this Triumphant Show to honour her Prince, and in a time of ſuch ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement heate, though this very day it was ſome-what qualified.</hi> The Feſtiuitie ended, and his Maieſtie and <pb n="22" facs="tcp:6423:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>his Highneſſe returned to the Counteſſes houſe, where they refreſhed and comforted themſelues with thoſe ſweet meates, which before were left ſtanding on the Table, eating none of the hot meat which was prouided, being aboundant and good; There vvas freſh drink allow'd. This Bounty continuing from the morning till night, with three Butteries, or Cellars, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundantly furniſhed. The Queene and the Lady <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanta</hi> returned to the Court, with the Lord <hi>Infante</hi> Cardinall; and his Maieſtie, and the Lord
<hi>Infante Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los,</hi> to the <hi>Pannaderia,</hi> to bring home the PRINCE of WALES, who entertained theſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, with the ſame reſpect, and loue they deſeru'd.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6423:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
